Finding Aid for Center for Human Growth and Development (University of Michigan) Records, 1963-2008
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Center for Human Growth and Development (University of Michigan) Records 1963-2008
University of Michigan. Center for Human Growth and Development.
2009104 Bimu 2
The University of Michigan Center for Human Growth and Development was established in 1964 to study the ways in which human beings grow and develop. It is an interdisciplinary department with faculty from a variety of the university's schools and colleges. The records date from 1963 to 2008 and include reports, committee files, administrative information and topical files.
2 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Records were received in August 2008 (Donor No. 10091 )
Periodic additions to the records are expected.
The record group is open without restriction.
The Center for Human Growth and Development (CHGD) was established by the Regents of the University of Michigan in 1964. It is a research center that reports to the Office of the Vice President of Research (OVPR). It is an interdisciplinary department with faculty from a variety of the university's schools and colleges, including biomedical, psychological and social science fields.
Its goal is to study the complex ways in which human beings grow and develop. According to the initial press release in 1964, the CHGD's four objectives were the following:
To coordinate, integrate, and conduct research on normal and abnormal human growth and development, including its biological, intellectual, behavioral, and social aspects
To identify and address problems of research that remain unsolved because of the lack of a multi-disciplinary approach
To provide new types of training programs for developmental scientists, especially flexible programs exposing trainees from several disciplines to a broader spectrum of knowledge than traditionally possible; and
To provide for the constant communication of ideas among scientists within the Center and the university, and to create a means by which knowledge gained from the research activities of the Center can be disseminated rapidly for the good of the public.
As of 2008, the CHGD had 31 faculty members who held tenure appointments in one of the university's 19 schools or colleges, and six faculty associates who held research appointments at CHGD.
Directors of the CHGD:
1963-1980 Robert E. Moyers
1980 Harold W. Stevenson (Acting)
1981 A. Rees Midgley
1982-1993 John Hagen
1994-2003 Betsy Lozoff
2004- Dan Keating
The records of the University of Michigan Center for Human Growth and Development (CHGD) date from 1963 to 2007 and divided into the five series: Reports, Committees, Administration, Publications and Visual Media.
Subjects:
Child development--Research.; Human growth--Research.; University of Michigan. Center for Human Growth and Development.
- Reports 1976-1998
  The Committees series, 1976-2008, contains meeting minutes for the General Membership and the Executive Committee as well as several ad hoc committees. The General Membership is comprised of the members of the faculty of CHGD. Its meeting minutes cover a period from 1979 to 2008. It should be noted that the meeting minutes began to be numbered in sequential order beginning in 1981. The Executive Committee is a smaller committee comprised of five elected faculty members and the CHGD director. It was set up to recommend and interpret overall policy for the CHGD. Its meeting minutes span 1976-2008. Its minutes are also sequentially numbered, beginning in 1980. The ad hoc committees include correspondence related to a number of temporary committees. The committees are the Membership and Review Committee, 1979-1984, Resources Committee, 1981-1985, Symposium Committee, 1984 and various committees, 1981.
  - Annual Reports (Box 1)
    - Annual Report 1977-1978, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Annual Report 1979-1980, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Interim Annual Report 1980 (Box 1)
    - Biennial Report 1982-1984 (Box 1)
    - Biennial Report 1984-1986 (Box 1)
    - Biennial Report 1986-1988 (Box 1)
    - Biennial Report 1988-1990 (Box 1)
    - Activities Report 1991-1996 (Box 1)
    - Activities Report 1996-1998 (Box 1)
    - Activities Report 1998-2000 (Box 1)
    - Activities Report 2000-2002 (Box 1)
  - Reviews
    - CHGD Retreat 1987, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Office of Vice President for Research Review 1991, 5 folders (Box 1)
    - External Review Briefing Book 1992, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Self-Study Report 1997, 5 folders (Box 1)
    - Self-Study Report 2002, 7 folders (Box 1)
  - Organizational Reports
    - Proposal for a Center for the Study of Human Development 1963 (Box 1)
    - A Building for the Center for Human Growth and Development a Proposal 1967 (Box 1)
  - Program Reports
    - Progress Report for the Development of Language Functions 1965 (Box 1)
    - Annual Report for the Development of Language Functions 1967 (Box 1)
    - Annual Report for the Development of Language Functions 1968 (Box 1)
- Committees 1975-2005
  The Administration series, 1975-2005, has a folder containing a few documents related to CHGD Policy Development from 1975 through 1989. It also contains all of the CHGD Retreat Agendas from 1997 to 2005. There is a Handbook of Administrative Polices, Procedures and Support Services from 1986. Finally, there are submission forms highlighting the creation of new courses, created between 1986 and 1999.
  - Executive Committee (Box 2)
    - Meeting Minutes 1976-2008, 18 folders (Box 2)
  - General Membership Committee
    - Meeting Minutes 1979-2008, 8 folders (Box 2)
  - Ad Hoc Committees
    - Membership and Review 1979-1984 (Box 2)
    - Resources 1981-1985 (Box 2)
    - Symposium 1984 (Box 2)
    - Various 1981 (Box 2)
- Administration 1975-2005
  - CHGD Policy Development 1975-1989 (Box 2)
  - CHGD Retreat Agendas 1997-2005 (Box 2)
  - Handbook of Administrative Polices, Procedures and Support Services 1986 (Box 2)
  - New Course Prospectus 1986-1999, 2 folders (Box 2)
- Publications 1965-2003
  The Publications series, 1965-2003, contains a bibliography of journal publications by faculty members of the CHGD. The years span from 1965 to 1975 and also include 1982. The series also contains CHGD Newsletters and pamphlets for events sponsored by CHGD.
  - Bibliography of Journal Publications 1965-1975, 1982 (Box 2)
  - CHGD Newsletter 1971-1974, 1980-1981, 1988-1991, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Event Pamphlets (Sole Sponsor) 1982-2003 (Box 2)
  - Event Pamphlets (Co-Sponsor) 1984-1997 (Box 2)
- Visual Media
  The Visual Media series contains a VHS videotape of a 1987 festschrift in honor of Harold Stevenson.
  - Harold Stevenson's Festschrift Banquet Videotape (VHS) 1996 (Box 2)
Related Material
Some additional records for the CHGD can also be found in the collection for the Office of Vice President for Research (OVPR). The OVPR was the reporting home of the CHGD.